so I have a few questions um that
usually come up in regard to one of your
essays or one of the talks we did in the
past called The Taming that sensual
itch and one of the common questions is
isn't there a danger of intensifying
craving by not giving in to the
potential edge of the body if one one
doesn't relieve the body's sexual
tension won't it increase and spill over
into more UNH wholesome
behaviors uh well we certainly increase
initially the pressure but whether it
spills over or not that mean it depends
on whether you act out of it or
not so it cannot Auto automatically
spill over unless you spill it
over so
the responsibility never really leaves
you the the the point where it
matters is the point of your choice and
your action so of course saying no to an
action so of course saying no to an
unrestrained
habit it's going to amplify The Habit
initially and there is no danger in that
the danger is in you perpetually acting
out of
habit there there's a assumption that uh
if you repress your desires you know you
are going you are going to that
repression will lead you to
automatically do bad things yeah exactly
yeah but that's not how things work I
think that probably came from some
School of Psychology or some Theory at
some point that repression we must
repress but I'm pretty sure that there
are plenty of schools even within the
worldly psychology they would refute and
dispute that is a factual truth right
because doesn't matter how much the
pressure builds up it cannot make you
act unless you choose to do
so so then people that um resort to the
view of oh repression is bad it will
make me act automatically are the people
that hold a view that they're not
responsible to begin
with so yes saying no to yourself
especially if you haven't been doing it
will hurt
exactly like with drawing from the drugs
would or any other
addiction but it still can't make the
drugs come to you on its
own or any addictive substance unless
you choose to do it yeah unless you
undermine your own decision to be
restrained so yeah you need to repress
things in order to pressurize them
sufficiently enough in order to contain
them in order to see the line where your
responsibility is and once that's
clarified uh that's how the mind grows
the Mind grows out of that
pressure If there is no pressure of
restraint there is no growth of Mind as
simple as
that everything you do about it is just
on the level of Wishful Thinking any
practices you might be doing any
meditation you might be doing if it's
not done on the basis of seeing the
danger in the slightest fault and sense
restraint is just wishful thinking
fantasy world you're building up the
mind is not growing the mind is just
becoming more equipped how to manage and
avoid its own
responsibility manage suffering and
avoid responsibility but if on the other hand
responsibility but if on the other hand
the mind is
pressured or
pressurized through sense restrain
through seeing the danger in this
slightest fault through withdrawal from
sensuality even if you don't think
about developing your mind further and
growing it it
will because the pressure makes you do
so so obviously you don't take all the
pressure all at once or expect to be
able to hold it all
overnight but if you have a
view that pressure is bad because I
might choose to do things and it's not
really my fault it's the pressure then
there is no development for you because
of that view
but if you don't hold that view even if
you keep failing to contain the pressure
and to build it up at least you're
working towards it because you're not
neglecting the
responsibility you're not covering it up
you're not justifying it so
it so
containing the mind confining it
building up the
pressure helps it grow exactly yeah
because you are Discerning helps it grow
outlines it for you
better doesn't make it spill out through
careless actions which blurs the
lines between the mental pressures and
your own choices and your own
fuel um so everything just becomes one
thing and you just sort of submit to it
but if you start uh building up the
pressure through the right sense
restraint virtue withraw from precepts
cacy it outlines the mind it outlines
the extent of that pressure that doesn't
come from you and then consequently it
outlines your own responsibility when
you choose to give in or blur the lines
yourself so you can see that I I can
choose to give into this pressure I can
choose not to I can choose not to and
that's already growth yeah recognizing
that choice it's already a form of
growth to the like to the to the full
extent recognizing that choice that's
the Detachment that one you be aiming
for yes so you detach yourself from your
mind when the mind is officially
pressurized and you haven't been acting
out of it that outlines it as a separate
entity and you don't have to be figuring
out what chitt nimita is and what all
these simil of taming the chitt are
you'll be seeing it because you
separated it from yourself through
pressurizing it correctly by making it
stand out basically by making it exactly
pressure out of the mind you start it
starts to stand out it almost gets
frustrated with the
you see the the boundary of
frustration you see the boundary of the
mood it comes out of its hiding any a
way like you you force it out exactly
yeah